上周我们学了公钥加密所需的数论知识
Last week, we learned a number theory
that's needed for public key encryption.
这周我们要用这些知识了，我们将构建
This week we're gonna put this knowledge
to work, and we're gonna construct a
许多安全的公钥加密机制。首先，我们需要定义
number of secure public key encryption
schemes. But first, we need to define what
什么是公钥加密，以及安全的公钥加密是什么意思？
is public key encryption, and what does it
mean for public key encryption to be
我提示大家，在公钥加密机制中
secure? So let me remind you that in a
public key encryption scheme, there is an
有一个加密算法记为E，还有个解密算法
encryption algorithm which is usually
denoted by E, and there's a decryption
我们记为D。不过这里的加密算法
algorithm which we denote by D. However
here, the encryption algorithm takes a
取一个公钥为输入，而解密算法取一个私钥为输入
public key, while the decryption algorithm
takes a secret key. This pair is called a
这一对叫做密钥对。公钥用于加密信息
key pair. And the public key is used for
encrypting messages while the secret key
私钥用于解密信息。那么这里，一个明文m
is used for decrypting messages. So in
this case a message m is encrypting using
使用公钥加密，得到密文c。类似地
the public key and what comes out of that
is the ciphertext c. And similarly the
把密文c交给解密算法，使用私钥
ciphertext is fed into the decryption
algorithm and using the secret key, what
解密算法的输出就是原明文m
comes out of the decryption algorithm is
the original message m. Now public key
公钥加密有许多应用。上周我们看了经典的应用
encryption has many applications. Last
week we saw the classic application which
比如会话建立，密钥交换，目前我们只看了
is session setup, namely, key exchange and
for now we're just looking at key exchange
仅对窃听攻击安全的密钥交换。如果大家还记得
that is secure against eavesdropping only.
And if you remember the way the protocol
这个协议的工作过程，Alice会产生一个公钥、私钥对
works, basically Alice, what she would do
is she would generate a public key secret
她会把公钥发给Bob。Bob会产生一个随机X
pair. She would send the public key to
Bob. Bob will generate a random X, which
X被作为共享密钥，然后Bob把X加密后发送给Alice
is gonna serve as their shared secret, and
then he sends X encrypted to Alice,
使用Alice的公钥进行加密。Alice可以解密，还原X
encrypted under her public key. Alice can
decrypt, recover X and now both of them
现在双方都有了这个共享密钥X了，他们可以使用它
来安全地互相通信
have this shared secret X which they can
use to communicate securely with one
攻击者当然只能看到公钥
another. The attacker, of course, all he
gets to see is just the public key, the
和使用公钥加密后的X，根据这些他不应该能
encryption of X under the public key, from
which he should not be able to get any
获得任何关于X的信息。我们要更精确地定义
information about X. And we are going to
define that more precisely to understand
不能学到任何关于X的信息是什么意思
what it means to not be able to learn
anything about X. Public key encryption
公钥加密实际上有很多应用。例如
actually has many other applications. For
example, it's very useful in
它在非互动应用中非常有用。考虑一个电子邮件系统为例
non-interactive applications. So think of
an email system for example. So here, Bob
这里Bob想发送电子邮件给Alice，随着Bob发送了这份邮件
wants to send mail to Alice, and as Bob
sends the email, the email passes from
电子邮件经由一个个邮件中转点，最终到达Alice
mail relay to mail relay until finally it
reaches Alice, at which point Alice should
Alice可以解密之。这样建立的电子邮件系统
decrypt. The way the email system is set
up, is designed for kind of
是为Bob发送邮件的非互动情形设计的
non-interactive settings where Bob sends
the email. And then Alice is supposed to
然后Alice应收到邮件，为解密邮件
receive it. And Alice should not be to
communicate with Bob in order to decrypt
Alice不应与Bob通信。这里，因为这种非互动性
the email. So in this case, because of the
non-interactivity, there's no opportunity
没有建立Alice和Bob之间的共享密钥的机会
for setting up a shared secret between
Alice and Bob. So in this case, what would
这里Bob会发送加密的邮件，使用Alice的公钥
happen is, Bob basically would, would send
the email encrypted, using Alice's, public
他发送了邮件，世界上任何人可以发送加密后的电子邮件
key. So he sends the email. Anyone in the
world can send the email encrypted to
给Alice，使用她的公钥。当Alice接收到邮件时
Alice, encrypted using her public key.
When Alice receives this email, she uses
她使用她的私钥来解密密文，还原明文
her secret key to decrypt the ciphertext and recover the plain text message.
当然这种系统有一个警告，事实上Bob
Of course the one caveat in a system like
this is that in fact Bob needs to somehow
需要通过某种方法知道Alice的公钥。目前我们还只是假设
obtain Alice's public key So for now we
are just going to assume Bob already has
Bob已经有了Alice的公钥，但待会当我们讨论
Alice's public key, but later on,
actually, when we talk about digital
数字签名时，我们会看到，这点使用所谓的
signatures we're gonna see how, this can
actually be done very efficiently using what's
公钥管理将非常有效，如我所说，我们待会再来看
called public key management and as I said
we'll actually get back to that at a later
我想让大家记住的主要是，公钥加密
time. But the main thing I want you to
remember, is that public key encryption is
用于会话建立。这在网络上很普遍
used for session setup. This is very
common on the web, where public key
公钥加密用于建立起一个浏览器和网页服务器之间的安全密钥
encryption is used to set up a secure key
between a web browser and, and web server.
公约加密对非互动的应用也很实用
And public key encryption is also very
useful for non-interactive applications,
这个世界的任何人，需要非互动地发送信息
where anyone in the world,
non-interactively, needs to send a message
给Alice时，可以使用Alice的公钥加密信息
to Alice, they can encrypt the message using
Alice's public key, and Alice can decrypt
Alice可以解密并还原明文。那么我来提示大家
and recover the plain text. So let me
remind you in a bit more detail what a
关于公钥加密系统的更多细节。公钥加密系统
由三个算法构成G,E,D
public key encryption system is. Well,
it's made up of three algorithms G, E, and
G叫做密钥生成算法
D. G is called the key generation algorithm.
Basically what it will do is it will
G会生成这个密钥对，即公钥和私钥。如此所写
generate this key pair, the public key and
the secret key. As written here, G takes
G无输入参数，但在现实中，G其实有一个参数
no arguments, but in real life, G actually
does take an argument called the security
叫做安全参数，指定了这个密钥生成算法将要生成的密钥大小
parameter which specifies the size of the
keys that are generated by this key
通常有这些加密算法
generation algorithm. Then there are these
encryption algorithms as usual that take a
它们取一个公钥和明文为输入，产生一个密文
public key and a message and produce a
ciphertext in a decryption algorithm that
在解密算法中，取对应私钥和密文为输入
takes the corresponding secret key and a
ciphertext and it produces a corresponding
产生对应明文。通常为求一致性，我们说
如果我们使用一个给定的公钥加密了一个明文
message. And as usual for consistency we
say that if we encrypt a message under a
然后我们用对应的私钥解密
given public key and then decrypt with a
corresponding secret key we should get the
我们应该可以获得原先的明文。现在，一个
公钥加密是安全的，是什么意思呢？
original message back. Now what does it
mean for a public key encryption to be
我想先从定义对抗窃听的安全性出发
secure? I'm going to start off by
defining, security against eavesdropping.
然后我们再定义对抗主动攻击的安全性
And then we're going to define security
against active attacks. So the way to
定义对抗窃听的安全性，与对称密码的情况很类似
define security against eavesdropping is
very similar to the symmetric case we've
上周我们已经看过，那么我们快速回顾一下
already this last week so we're gonna go
through this quickly just as a review.
这个攻击游戏如下定义。我们定义两个实验
Basically the attack game is defined as
follows. We defined these two experiments,
实验0和实验1。在两个实验中
experiment zero and experiment one. At in
either experiment the challenger is gonna
挑战者都会生成一对公钥和私钥
generate a public and a secret key pair. He's gonna give the public
他把公钥给攻击者，攻击者产生两个信息m0和m1
key to the adversary. The adversary's
gonna output two messages m0 and m1 of
长度相同，然后攻击者会得到m0或m1的加密
equal length and then what he gets back is
either the encryption of m0 or the
在实验0中，他会得到m0的加密
encryption of m1. In experiment zero he
gets the encryption of m0. In experiment
在实验1中，他会得到m1的加密。然后攻击者要识别
one he gets the encryption of m1. And then
the adversary is supposed to say which one
他得到的是哪个信息的加密。他得到的是m0还是m1的加密？
did he get. Did he get the encryption of
m0 or did he get the encryption of m1? So
那么在这个有效中，攻击者只会得到一个密文
in this game, the attacker only gets one
ciphertext. This corresponds to an
这个对应于窃听攻击中他监听到的密文C
eavesdropping attack where he simply
eavesdropped on that ciphertext C. And now
现在他的目标是分辨出密文C是m0还是m1的加密
his goal is to tell whether the ciphertext
C is the encryption of M0 or M1. No
对密文C的篡改是不被允许的。通常我们说
tampering on the ciphertext C is allowed
just yet. And as usual we say that the
这个公钥加密机制是语义安全的，如果攻击者不能
public key encryption scheme is
semantically secure if the attacker cannot
区分实验0和实验1。换句话说
distinguish experiment zero from
experiment one. In other words he cannot
他不能区分他获得的是m0还是m1的加密
tell whether he got the encryption of M0,
or the encryption of M1. Before we move on
在我们讨论主动攻击之前，我想简单提一下这个定义
to active attacks, I want to mention a
quick relation between the definition we
与对称密码的窃听安全的定义之间的关系
just saw, And the definition of, of
eavesdropping security for symmetric
如果大家还记得，当我们讨论对称密码的窃听攻击时
ciphers. If you remember, when we talked
about eavesdropping security for symmetric
我们区分了两种情况，密钥只使用一次
ciphers, we distinguished between the case
where the key is used once, and the case
和密钥使用多次。事实上我们看到了
where the key is used multiple times. And,
in fact we saw that, there's a clear
有明确的区分。例如，一次性密码本是安全的，
如果密钥只被用于加密当个明文
separation. For example, the onetime pad.
Is secure if the key is used to encrypt a
但如果密钥用于加密多个明文，将是完全不安全的了
single message, but is completely insecure
if the key is used to encrypt multiple
如果大家记得，事实上我们有两个不同的定义
messages. And in fact we had two different
definitions if you remember we had a
一个是一次性安全，我们还有另一个不同的定义
definition for one-time security, and then
we had a separate definition, which was
更强一点，当密钥被使用多次
stronger, when the key was used multiple
times. The definition that I showed you on
上一张幻灯片里的定义与对称密码的一次性安全
the previous slide's very similar to the
definition of one time security for
很类似。事实上，对于公钥加密
symmetric ciphers. And in fact, it turns
out that for public key encryption, if a
如果系统的一次性密钥是安全的，那么它对多次密钥
system is secure under a onetime key, in a
sense, it's also secure for a many time
也是安全的。换句话说，如果我们不必赋予攻击者
key. So in other words, we don't have to
explicitly give the attacker the ability
请求加密他选择的明文的能力。因为他可以自己
to, request encryptions of messages of his
choice. Because he could just create those
创建这些加密。他有了公钥，因此他可以
encryptions all by himself. He is given
the public key, and therefore he can by
自己加密任何他喜欢的明文。因此从某种意义上
himself encrypt any message he likes. As a
result any public key secret pair in some
公钥私钥对天生就是用来加密多个信息的
sense inherently is used to encrypt
multiple messages because the attacker
因为攻击者可以加密很多他选择的明文
could have just encrypted many, many
messages of his choice using the given
使用我们第一步给他的给定的公钥。所以事实上
public key that we just gave him in the
first step. And so, as a result in fact,
一次性安全的定义足以蕴涵着多次安全
the definition of one time security is
enough to imply many time security and
这就是为什么我们称这个概念是
选择明文攻击下的不可区分性
that's why we refer to the concept as
indistinguishability under a chosen plain
这只是稍微解释了为什么在公钥加密的设定里
text attack. So this is just a minor point
to explain why the settings of public
我们不需要更复杂的定义
encryption, we don't need a more
complicated definition to capture
来理解窃听安全。现在我们理解了窃听安全性
eavesdropping security. Now that we
understand eavesdropping security, let's
我们来看更强大的攻击者，他们可以实施主动攻击
look at more powerful adversaries that can
actually mount active attacks. So, in
特别地，我们看电子邮件的例子。那么这里我们有
particular, let's look at the email
example. So here, we have our friend Bob
我们的朋友Bob想发送邮件给他的朋友Caroline
who wants to send mail to his friend
Caroline. And Caroline happens to have, an
Caroline正好在Gmail上有帐号。过程如下
account at Gmail. And the way this works
is basically, the email is sent to the
这份加密的邮件发送给Gmail服务器，Gmail服务器解密邮件
Gmail server, encrypted. The Gmail server
decrypts the email, looks at the, intended
查看接收方，如果接收方是Caroline
recipients. And then, if it's, the
intended recipient is Caroline, it
它会把这份邮件转发给Caroline。如果接收方是攻击者
forwards the email to Caroline. If the
intended recipient is the attacker, it
它会把邮件转发给攻击者。这与Gmail的工作方式类似
forwards the email to the attacker. This
is similar to how Gmail actually works
因为发送方会通过SSL把邮件加密后发给Gmail服务器
because the sender would send the email
encrypted over SSL to the Gmail server.
Gmail服务器会中断SSL连接，然后把邮件转发给合适的接收方
The Gmail server would terminate the SSL
and then forward the email to the
现在假设Bob加密了邮件
appropriate recipients. Now suppose Bob
encrypts the email using a system that
使用的系统允许攻击者篡改密文，且不会被检测到
allows the adversary to tamper with the
ciphertext without being detected. For
例如，想象这份邮件是使用计数器模式加密的
example, imagine this email is encrypted
using Counter Mode, or something like
(参考第7章1节，当时讲的是篡改CBC的IV导致重定向)
或类似的。然后当攻击者截获了这个邮件，
他可以改变接收方
that. Then when the attacker intercepts
this email, he can change the recipient,
这样使得接收方变成了attacker@gmail.com
so that now the recipient says
attacker@gmail.com, and we know that for
我们知道对于计数器模式，比如说，这是非常容易做到的
Counter Mode, for example, this is quite
easy to do. The attacker knows that the
攻击者知道邮件是发往Caroline的，他只对邮件内容感兴趣
email is intended for Caroline, he is just
interested in the email body. So he can
所以他可以把邮件的接收方改成attacker@gmail.com
easily change the email recipient to
attacker@gmail.com and now when the server
这样当服务器接收到邮件时，他会解密，
看到接收方是攻击者
receives the email, he will decrypt it,
see that the recipient is supposed to be
然后就把邮件转发给了攻击者
attacker, and forward the body to the
attacker. And now the attacker was able to
现在攻击者可以读到邮件的内容了，
这些内容本该给Caroline的
read the body of the email that was
intended for Caroline. So this is a
这是一个经典的主动攻击的例子，大家注意
classic example of an active attack, and
you notice what the attacker could do
攻击者只能解密接收方是攻击者的邮件
here, is it could decrypt any ciphertext
where the intended recipient is to:
也就是以"致攻击者"开头的明文所对应的密文
attacker. So any ciphertext where the plain
text begins with the words "to: attacker". So our goal is
我们的目标是设计安全的公钥系统，即使攻击者可以篡改密文
to design public key systems that are
secure, even if the attacker can tamper
还可以解密特定的密文
with ciphertext and possibly decrypt
certain cyphertexts. And again, I want to
我想再强调，这里攻击者的目标是获得明文内容
emphasize that here the attacker's goal
was to get the message body. The attacker
攻击者已经知道了，邮件是给Caroline的
already knew that the email is intended
for Caroline. And all he had to do was
他只需要改变接收方。所以这种篡改就引入了
just change the intended recipient. So
this tampering attack motivates the
选择密文安全的定义。事实上这是公钥加密的
definition of chosen ciphertext security.
And in fact this is the standard notion of
标准安全性观念。我来解释这个攻击
security for public key encryption. So let
me explain how the attack [here procedes] and as I
如我所说，我们的目标是构建安全的系统
said our goal is to build systems that are
secure under this very, very conservative
使用非常保守的加密观念。那么我们有一个加密机制(G,E,D)
notion of encryption. So we have an
encryption scheme (G, E, D). And let's say
我们定义在明文空间和密文空间(M,C)上
that's defined over a message space and
a ciphertext (M, C) and as usual we're
通常我们定义两个实验，实验0和实验1
gonna define two experiments, experiment
zero, and experiment one. So 'b' here
那么这里的b表示挑战者是实现实验0
says whether the challenger is
implementing experiment zero or experiment
或是实验1。挑战者开始时生成一对公钥和私钥
one. The challenger begins by generating a
public key and a secret key, and then gives
然后把公钥给攻击者。现在攻击者可以说
the public key to the adversary. Now the
adversary can say, "Well, here are a bunch
这里有很多密文，请为我解密它们
of ciphertexts, please decrypt them for
me." So here the adversary submits
这里攻击者提交了密文C1，他获得了密文C1的解密，即M1
ciphertext C1 and he gets the decryption
of ciphertext C1, namely M1. And he gets
攻击者可以一次次地这么做，那么他提交了密文C2，获得解密
to do this again and again, so he submits
ciphertext C2, and he gets the decryption,
也就是M2，然后密文C3，获得解密M3，等等。。
which is M2, ciphertext C3, and he gets
the decryption M3, and so on and so forth.
最终，攻击者说，游戏结束了
Finally, the adversary says, "This
squaring phase is over," and now he
现在他提交两个等长度的明文M0和M1
submits basically two equal length
messages, M0 and M1 as normal, and he
他会收到挑战密文C，也就是M0或M1的加密
receives in response the challenge
ciphertext C, Which is the encryption of M
取决于我们是在实验0还是实验1
zero or the encryption of M one. Depending
on whether we're in experiment zero or
现在，攻击者可以继续提交这些密文询问
experiment one. Now, the adversary
can continue to issue these ciphertext
(这个版本的定义是IND-CCA2)
他可以继续请求解密。那么他提交了一个密文
queries. So he can continue to issue,
decryption requests. So he submits a
(若攻击者不能继续询问；就是IND-CCA1的定义)
他获得了他提交的密文的解密，但当然
ciphertext, and he gets a decryption of
that ciphertext, but of course, now, there
必须警告，如果攻击者可以提交他选择的任意密文
has to be a caveat. If the attacker could
submit arbitrary ciphertext of his choice,
那么他可以破解这个挑战。他只需提交
of course, he could break the challenge.
What he would do is he would submit the
这个挑战密文C，作为解密请求。然后他被告知
challenge ciphertext C as a decryption
query. And then he would be told whether
他在挑战阶段获得的是M0还是M1的加密结果
in the challenge phase he was given the
encryption of M0 or the encryption of M1.
因为我们有这么一个限制，攻击者可以提交
As a result we put this limitation here,
that says that he can in fact submit any
任何他选择的密文，除了挑战密文
ciphertext of his choice except. For the
challenge ciphertext. So the attacker
那么攻击者可以询问他选择的任何密文的解密
could ask for the decryption of any
ciphertext of his choice other than the
除了挑战密文。即使攻击者有所有这些的解密
challenge ciphertext. And even though he
was given all these decryptions, he still
他依然不能分辨出他得到的是M0还是M1的加密
shouldn't be able to tell whether he was
given the encryption of M0 or the
所以大家注意，这是一个非常保守的定义
encryption of M1. So you notice this is a
very conservative definition. It gives the
他赋予了攻击者比我们上一张幻灯片里看到的更多的能力
attacker more power than what we saw in
the previous slide. On the previous slide,
上一张幻灯片里，攻击者只能解密以"致攻击者"开头的信息
the attacker could only decrypt messages
where the plain text began with the words
这里，攻击者可以解密任何他选择的密文
"to: attacker". Here, we're saying the attacker
can decrypt any ciphertext of his choice,
只要提交的密文与挑战密文C不同
as long as it's different from the
challenge ciphertext C. Okay? And then his
然后攻击者的目标是，判断挑战密文是M0还是M1的加密
goal is to say whether the challenge
ciphertext is the encryption of M0 or the
通常，如果攻击者不能做到，换句话说
encryption of M1. And as usual, if he
can't do that, in other words, his
他的表现在实验0和实验1中是一样的
behavior in experiment zero is basically
the same as his behavior in experiment
那么他不能区分M0与M1的加密
one, so he wasn't able to distinguish the
encryption of M0 from the encryption of
即使他拥有这么多的能力。那么我们说
M1, even though he had all this power. Then
we say that the system is chosen
这个系统是选择密文CCA安全的。
有时有一个缩写词
ciphertext secure, CCA secure. And
sometimes there is an acronym, the acronym
对选择密文攻击的不可区分性
for this is indistinguishability under a
chosen ciphertext attack, but I'm just
我记为CCA安全。那么我们看这如何抓住了
gonna say CCA secured. So let's see how
this captures, the email example we saw
我们前面看的电子邮件的例子的特点。那么假设
使用的加密系统满足
before. So suppose the encryption system
being used is such that just given the
给定信息的加密，攻击者可以改变接收方
encryption of a message the attacker can
change the intended recipient from to
从"致Alice"改成"致Charlie"，那么我们可以这样赢得游戏
Alice say to, to Charlie. Then here's how
we would win the CCA game. Well in the
第一步攻击者当然得到了公钥，那么
first step he's given the public key of
course. And then what the attacker will do
攻击者会发出两个等长度的明文
is he would issue two equal length
messages, namely in the first message, the
第一个明文内容是0，第二个明文内容是1
body is zero. In the second message the
body is one. But both messages are
两个明文都给Alice，Alice回复后，攻击者会得到密文C
intended for Alice. And in response, he
would be given the challenge ciphertext C.
那么现在我们有我们的挑战密文C了
Okay, so now here we have our challenge
ciphertext C. Now what the attacker is
现在攻击者会使用他的能力去修改接收方
gonna do is he's gonna use his, his
ability here to modify the intended
他会返回给Alice一个密文C'
recipient. And he's gonna send back a
ciphertext C', where C' is the encryption
C'是给Charlie的明文加密结果，其内容是挑战密文的内容b
of the message to Charlie with body being
the challenge body b. So if you remember is
那么如果大家记得，是0或是1.现在因为明文不同
either zero or one. Now, because the plain
text is different, we know that the
我们知道密文也不同，那么特别地
ciphertext must also be different. So in
particular, C prime must be different from
C'一定和挑战密文C不一样，对吧？那么C'一定不同于C
the challenge ciphertext C, yeah? So the
C prime here must be different from C. And
因此，可怜的挑战者现在必须解密，根据CCA游戏的定义
as a result, the poor challenger now has
to decrypt by definition of the CCA game.
挑战者必须解密任何不同于挑战密文的密文
The challenger must decrypt any ciphertext
that's not equal to a challenge
那么挑战者解密了，给攻击者解密结果M'
ciphertext. So the challenger decrypts
give the adversary M prime. Basically he
他给了攻击者b，现在攻击者可以输出挑战结果b
gave the adversary B, and now the
adversary can output the challenge B and
他以优势1赢得了这个游戏。那么他对这个游戏的优势是1
he wins the game with advantage one. So
he's advantage with this particular scheme
因为攻击者能够改变挑战密文
is one. So, simply because the attacker
was able to change the challenge ciphertext
从一个接收方改到另一个，使得他能以优势1赢下这个CCA游戏
from one recipient to another that
allows him to, to win the CCA game with
如我所说，选择密文安全事实上是
advantage one. So as I said, chosen
ciphertext security turns out actually is
公钥加密的正确的观念
the correct notion of security for public
key encryption systems. And it's a very,
这是个非常有趣的概念，对吧？即使攻击者有这能力
very interesting concept, right? Basically, somehow even though the attacker has this ability
能解密任何他想解密的密文，挑战密文除外
to decrypt anything he wants. Other than
the challenge ciphertext, still he can't
他依然不能学到挑战密文是什么。那么本章余下的目标
learn what the challenge ciphertext is.
And so the goal for the remainder of this module
其实也包括下一章，目标是构建CCA安全的系统
and actually the next module as well, is
to construct CCA secure systems. It's
很惊人的是，这是可以做到的
actually quite remarkable that this is
achievable and I'm going to show you
我会告诉大家怎么搞。事实上我们构建的这些CCA安全系统
exactly how to do it. And in fact those
CCA secure systems that we build are the
就是在现实中使用的系统。每次系统试图
ones that are used in the real world. And
every time a system has tried to deploy
布置一个不是CCA安全的公钥加密机制时
a public key encryption mechanism that's not
CCA secure someone has come up with an
都有人提出攻击并破解了它。我们将看到这些攻击的几个例子
attack and was able to break it. And we're
going to see some of these example attacks
在下面几节里
actually in the next few segments.